Don't sleep there.
别睡在那里
Hey!
喂
Hurry up.
快点起来
Hey, come on.
喂 起来啊
My big brother.
我的哥哥
My big brother is in high school.
我的哥哥是一个高中生
At home, he dresses sloppy and he's untidy.
在家里穿得很邋遢
But when he goes out, he acts totally cool.
但当他出门时 却装得很酷
His character at home is totally different than when he's not.
他在家里跟在外面的个性完全不一样
When he's with friends, he's incredibly chill.
他和朋友在一起时 非常有气度
No problem. Don't worry about it.
没关系 别担心
Let's go.
走
Then we told each other how we felt!
然后我们告诉对方彼此的感受
-You drank my tea, didn't you? -No!
-你喝了我的茶 对吗？ -没有
But at home, he is unbelievably stingy.
但在家里 他超级小气
-I'm sorry! -You did drink it!
-对不起 -你喝了？
Yes, I did! I did drink it!
没错 是我喝的
My brother wants people to like him.
我哥希望大家都喜欢他
I think that's all he thinks about.
我觉得他满脑子只有这件事
But if my brother acts like that…
但像我哥哥这样的行为…
"Will he
“他究竟
be able to grow up to be a proper adult?"
能够长大成为真正的大人吗？”
Hey!
喂
Come on. Let's go.
起来啦
Sleep in your room!
回你房间睡
Shuji.
哥哥
Are you a cow? Or a horse?
你是牛 还是马？
What the heck is he dreaming about?
这家伙到底在做什么梦？
Ours is the only class that hasn't decided on a project for the festival.
我们是唯一还没有决定 文化祭活动的班级
What's your problem, you people?
你们在搞什么？
Who's in charge of festival planning?
文化祭是谁负责的？
Isn't it Bando?
不是坂东吗？
-That's right! It's Bando. -Gosh, what a pain.
-没错 是坂东 -麻烦死啦
Oh, it's you, Bando?
是坂东啊
Spend this time deciding what to do.
花点时间决定我们究竟要办什么活动
Get up here.
快点 上来
-What a pain. -The floor's all yours.
-真麻烦 -舞台交给你啦
What do you want to do for the festival?
文化祭你们想做什么？
You guys say something.
你们也说句话呀
We're already doing a live show in the gym!
我们在体育馆已经有表演了
-All new material!
-全新题材
-We're in sync!
-心有灵犀
-This must be destiny!
-这一定是命运
You guys are a pain.
烦死人啦
-Doesn't anyone want to do anything? -I know!
-没有人有提案吗？ -我知道啦
Let's invite a celebrity!
请艺人来
-Nice! -Good idea!
-很好 -好主意
Then we should invite Masaharu Fukuyama.
那就请福山雅治来
-No! Ken Matsudaira. -I know! Akiko Yada!
-不行 找松平健啦 -我知道啦 找矢田亚希子
Akiko Yada is the best! Don't forget her!
矢田亚希子最棒啦 别忘了她
Hey! Cut the bullshit ideas!
喂 少出这种鬼主意
Then you decide.
那你来决定
Fine!
知道啦
Then I can decide for everyone, right?
我可以替大家决定 对吗？
-Go right ahead. -Bando's choice!
-快决定 -坂东的选择
Yes!
好耶
We'll do a haunted house.
我们来办鬼屋
Just a dark room with Kotani standing inside.
黑暗的房间里 只有小谷站着
Very realistic!
非常逼真
Starring, Nobuko Kotani.
主演是小谷信子
Props, Nobuko Kotani. Scenery, Nobuko Kotani.
道具是小谷信子 布景是小谷信子
That settles it!
就这么决定啦
Don't be stupid! One person can't do all that!
别傻啦 一个人怎么能做这么多事？
Then I assign Akira Kusano to do the grunt work.
那苦差事就都交给草野彰
"Hey! Cut the bullshit ideas!"
“喂 少出这种鬼主意”
And what are you going to do, Bando?
那你要做什么 坂东？
I'll just watch to make sure Kusano and Kotani do their jobs.
我会监督草野和小谷 确保他们完成任务
That's all. Any objections?
就这样 有人反对吗？
Me.
我反对
Settled by majority vote.
那就少数服从多数
-It's settled!
-搞定啦
Is that what you guys want?
你们想要这么做吗？
Are you complaining about what we decided?
你们对我们的决定有意见吗？
That's not what I mean.
我不是那个意思
You're good with it?
你们都没意见吗？
-Okay. That settles it. -That settles it?
-好 那就这么决定啦 -就这样？
Okay. Time to take attendance. Aoi.
好 开始点名啦
But you know, this could be our chance.
不过这也许是我们的机会
If Nobuta is a success at the festival,
如果野猪在文化祭上大放异彩
everyone will see her differently.
大家都会对她另眼相看
But of all possible things, this is a haunted house, man.
但却偏偏要做鬼屋
No way the two of you can pull it off.
你们两个人是不可能办到的
It's not two. There are three of us.
不是两个人 我们有三个人
If we're doing this…
如果要做…
then let's have fun.
就开心地做
That's right.
没错
Let's have fun doing it.
我们就开心地做
How can you be so easygoing about this?
你们怎么可以这么轻松啊？
If we blow it, Nobuta will get bullied even more.
要是搞砸的话 野猪会被欺负得更惨
What are you going to do, producer Shuji Kiritani?
改造者桐谷修二 你打算怎么做？
What are you going to do?
你打算怎么做？
What's wrong?
怎么啦？
Nothing.
没什么
Why are you watching this scary movie?
为什么看这么恐怖的电影？
We're doing a haunted house at the school festival.
我们要在文化祭办一个鬼屋
Oh, nice. A haunted house.
很棒呀 是鬼屋啊
That's freaking me out!
吓死我啦！
What's freaking you out? I don't get it.
你在怕什么？我完全不懂
The scariest haunted house in my life was
我这辈子见过最可怕的鬼屋
when this man was just standing there in the dark,
是一个男子站在黑暗之中
dressed like a regular businessman.
他穿得像个一般的上班族
He stood there drearily with his back facing me.
他阴沉地站在那里背对着我
That's creepy!
好诡异
I couldn't see his face,
我看不到他的脸
but since he didn't move an inch, I thought,
但他一动不动 我心想
"This is probably a mannequin!"
“这到底是不是个假人？”
But I couldn't make myself get close!
但我就是没办法靠近
That was seriously scary.
真的好可怕
I like that! We could make that with a mannequin.
我喜欢这点子 我们可以用假人
And dangle konnyaku and slap it against people's faces.
然后挂着魔芋 有人来时就甩到他们脸上
Right. Konnyaku. Write that down.
对 魔芋 写下来
What are you doing for the festival, Shuji?
哥 你们文化祭要做什么？
What?
什么？
A haunted house.
鬼屋
A haunted house?
鬼屋？
Really? Nice! That sounds like fun.
真的吗？真棒 听起来很有趣
-Can I go? -No, don't go.
-我可以去吗？ -不行 不准去
-How come? Why not? -I'll be busy.
-为什么？为什么不行？ -我会很忙的
I won't tell anyone you're a sloppy mess at home.
我不会跟别人说你在家里很邋遢
Don't you dare go.
你敢去就给我试试看
-Why? -Don't you dare!
-为什么？ -绝对不准
There's a dumpling stand!
有团子的摊位啊
You're not going.
你不准去
I'm home.
我回来啦
Mom isn't home yet?
你妈还没回来吗？
No.
还没
She said she'll buy croquettes.
她说会买可乐饼
You've got a festival, right?
你们要举办文化祭啊？
Yes.
对
Hey, James!
喂 詹姆斯
Help with the paper-mache.
过来帮忙做纸模型
We're helping.
我们在帮忙啊
-We're helping, right? -Yes.
-我们在帮忙 对吗？ -对
Yes, we're helping.
对啊 我们都在帮忙
You're not helping at all!
你们根本没帮上忙吗
Those two will never finish anyway.
光靠他们两个人永远也做不完
-Real quick? -A quick job!
-速战速决？ -速战速决
-Why not? -Let's do it!
-当然好啊 -来呀
Let's do this! Nice and quick!
来呀 速战速决
A nice quick paper-mache job!
速战速决做纸模型
Hey, everyone!
各位
All the girls in class A are running a dumpling stand wearing kimonos.
A班的女生全都穿着和服卖团子
-Kimonos?
-和服？
Let me see!
让我看看
Kimonos?
和服？
Is that Mariko Uehara?
那是上原真理子吗？
Mariko Uehara?
上原真理子？
-Shuji! -What?
-修二 -什么？
It's Mariko Uehara in a kimono!
是穿和服的上原真理子
That way!
那边
Hurry it up!
快一点
I thought you were wearing a kimono.
我还以为你穿着和服
Do you have time on the day of the festival?
文化祭那天你有空吗？
Let's walk around together.
一起去逛逛呀
I doubt I will.
不知道我有没有空
You've got a little time, right?
总会有一点时间吗？
I'll go around in my kimono.
我会穿着和服的
-Your kimono? -Yes.
-和服？ -对啊
A kimono sounds nice.
和服听起来挺不错
I bet you'll look great in it.
你穿起来一定很好看
Shuji!
修二
-Perfect timing! -What is it?
-你来得正好 -怎么啦？
We'll never finish making the costumes in time.
我们会来不及做好服装
-I'm the leader of the drama club. -Yes?
-我是戏剧社的社长 -什么？
-You're good with needles. -You bet.
-你很会缝纫 对吗？ -当然
Please! I'm begging you!
拜托啦 求求你
No way! Never!
不行啦
I just need a little help! Please!
我只是需要一点帮助 拜托
My best friend! My bosom buddy! Please!
我最好的朋友 我的好兄弟 求你啦
-I really-- -Fine!
-我真的… -好啦
-Thank you! These are the directions! -Okay.
-谢谢 按照这个缝 -好
-Thank you! Sorry! -Fine.
-谢谢 抱歉 -好的
-Shuji!
-修二
We're doing a fashion show on the day of the festival.
我们要在文化祭当天办时装秀
We need someone to take photos.
需要找人拍照
I am seriously busy.
我真的很忙
-But you're such a good photographer! -Please!
但你不是很会拍照吗？
Oh, fine. What about a camera?
好吧 那相机呢？
-Bring yours. -Yes.
-带你的就好啦 -对啊
Mine?
我的？
Of course. Every photographer does.
当然啦 摄影师都会带自己的相机
Okay. I'll take great photos.
好的 我会好好拍的
-All right!
-太好啦！
-Thanks! Bye! -Sure.
-谢谢 再见 -没问题
What a pain.
真麻烦
Kiritani! Come over here!
桐谷 过来一下
What?
什么？
You're a good singer, right?
你很会唱歌 对吗？
-Let's make a trio. -No, it's okay. Please. No!
-组成三人组 -不 不必啦 拜托 不要啊
Wait! Don't! Please!
等等 不要啊
What?
什么？
It's just you two?
就你们两个？
Where's everyone else?
其他人？
They all went home.
全都回家啦
For real?
真的吗？
What are we supposed to do?
我们该怎么做？
Can we even finish it?
能做得完吗？
Don't panic.
别慌张
How can you be so calm?
你怎能这么冷静？
When doing simple tasks like this,
做这种简单的工作
you feel like a monk meditating.
感觉就像是和尚打坐
So we'll just work together, the three of us.
所以我们三个人就一起努力
Yip yip.
嗯嗯
Hold on.
等一下
That's all you've done in one day?
你们一天只做了这些？
No! We started three days ago!
不对 我们三天前就开始啦
What? Three days…
什么？三天…
So this angle is 30 degrees.
这个角度是30度
And the length of this is the radius of the circle, so it's two.
然后这个长度是圆形的半径 所以是二
This is two. Then…
是二 然后…
Oh, no! My right hand!
不！我的右手
Why did you write "celebration"?
怎么可以写“祝”？
You're supposed to write "cursed"!
不是应该要写“咒”吗？
Later!
再见
See you. Make sure you watch it.
再见 一定要看哦
Sounds nice.
听起来不错
-You guys, you better watch it. -I will.
-你们一定要看啊 -我会看的
Shuji!
修二
Look. We've made lots of progress.
你看 我们有很大的进展
Now we just need the thing with the head that falls off.
现在只需要做掉下来的那颗头
What's he doing here?
他在这里做什么？
The frightening three-eyed dog. Woof!
可怕的三眼狗 汪
Are you kidding? You call that frightening?
开什么玩笑？那叫可怕？
I'll now plot small a vector and small b vector.
我现在要画出向量a和向量b
Okay.
好啦
BC vector here and AO vector are equal.
这边的向量BC跟向量AO相同
Why's that? Because they're parallel.
为什么？因为是平行的
You know what?
你知道吗？
No matter what I do, I never feel like it's much fun.
不管做什么 我都觉得不快乐
Things to me only seem fun when I think about them later.
我觉得要等事后回想起来 才会觉得快乐
What do you mean?
什么意思？
When I play video games and stuff, they're not fun when I'm playing.
当我打电动的时候 并不觉得快乐
But when I remember them while I'm studying, I think it was fun.
但读书时回想起来 才会觉得快乐
We may not realize what's fun until after it happens.
可能要等经历过之后 才会知道什么是快乐
I wonder if we'll remember a few years down the road.
不知道几年后我们会不会记得
Remember what?
记得什么？
The three of us making the mannequins early in the morning,
我们三个一大早就在做假人
or picking susuki grass in the late afternoon.
或是在傍晚时去采芒草
I wonder if in a few years we'll remember these things
不知道几年后 我们会不会记得这些事？
and think they were fun.
而且觉得很快乐
45TH SUMIDAGAWA HIGH SCHOOL FESTIVAL
（隅田川高中第45届文化祭）
Pretty darn scary!
很可怕耶
This turned out good! Right?
成果不错 对不对？
Right?
对吗？
D…
爸…
Dad…
爸爸
It looks like your dad?
那长得像你爸爸吗？
Want to call it "Kotani Papa"?
那要叫这个假人小谷爸爸吗？
Kotani Papa.
小谷爸爸
Papa.
爸爸
When you said "Dad," did you mean your stepdad?
你刚刚说的“爸爸” 是指你的继父吗？
I mean,
我是说
you said your mom remarried, but you can't call her new husband "Dad."
你说过你妈再婚 但你不被允许叫他爸爸 对吗？
Dad!
爸爸
Oh, sorry.
抱歉
I married your mom,
虽然我娶了你妈
but I'm not your dad.
但我不是你爸
Strikeout!
三振出局
But I bet you think of him as "Dad," don't you?
不过你还是想把他当爸爸？
Yip yip.
嗯嗯
I don't think that's your business.
那不关你的事
You think so?
是吗？
Do you?
是这样吗？
How come, Shuji?
为什么 修二？
Talk to me, Shuji!
修二 你说呀
Delphine!
戴菲尼
Nothing's changed.
一点都没变啊
You mean, you went to high school here?
你以前念这所高中吗？
Yes.
是啊
I wrote this graffiti.
这是我刻的
HEY BABY, I'LL BECOME HIDEKICHI
（我要成为英吉）
"I'll become Hidekichi."
“我要成为英吉”
Who's Hidekichi?
英吉是谁？
Hideyoshi.
秀吉
It's Toyotomi Hideyoshi.
是丰臣秀吉
I was depressingly stupid.
我当时真是蠢到极点
I thought it was pronounced "Hidekichi."
我一直以为是念“英吉”
I came to carve it over again, but I think I'll leave it.
我原本想来重新刻一个 但想想还是算啦
Right?
-对吗？ -是
As a memory of when I was colossally stupid,
当作纪念我最愚蠢的时期
I'll leave it as is.
我就不重新刻啦
Okay?
你们说是吗？
Yes.
是的
Bye.
再见
Why's the last thing you're making a mole?
为什么最后要做一只鼹鼠？
It's a bat.
是蝙蝠
Say, did you know?
你们知道吗？
Mole's live all alone in their hole.
鼹鼠独自住在洞穴里
But when it's time to mate, they find themselves a mate. Perverts!
但当需要交配时 它们就会去找另一半 好变态哦
How?
要怎么找？
When it's digging, it finds a woman, they hug and get it on!
它们挖洞时会找到一个姐姐抱紧紧 然后就搞在一起啦
The odds of that must be pretty darn low.
那几率一定很低
Yes. It's all underground.
是啊 它们都生活在地底下
But if they do actually meet up,
但如果它们真的碰面啦
that's a real miracle, right?
那真的是奇迹 对吗？
Yes. A miracle!
没错 奇迹
Yes! It's done!
好耶 完成啦
Okay, a photo for the memories.
那就拍张照纪念
Let's go.
要拍啦
Good idea.
好主意
Okay.
来呀
Say "cheese."
说茄子
-Hey. -What?
-喂 -干吗？
Eats!
去吃饭
-Not going. -Then how about food?
-不要 -那吃醋饭吗？
Bad joke. No good.
不好笑
KOTANI HOUSE OF HORROR
（小谷鬼屋）
-It's about to start! -It's starting!
-要开始啦 -快开始啦
-What we've all been waiting for! -It's coming soon now!
-大家期待已久的 -马上就要开始啦
-We've all been waiting! -It's the Sumidagawa High Festival!
-我们期待很久啦 -今天是隅田川高中文化祭
-The opening!
-开幕式
Shuji!
修二
-Shuji! -What is it?
-修二 -怎么啦？
Shuji…
修二
What the heck is this?
这是怎么回事？
KOTANI
（小谷）
That Kotani says she'll still do it.
小谷说她还是想办鬼屋
Kotani's the type that holds a grudge.
小谷是那种会记仇的人
Whoever did it better say their prayers.
做这种事的人最好开始祷告啊
What? Wasn't it you who did it?
什么？不是你们做的吗？
We wouldn't do this.
我们才不会做这种事
-We wouldn't go to this trouble. -We sure wouldn't.
-我们才不想自找麻烦 -就是说啊
We've got to get ready for the fashion show!
我们还要为时装秀做准备
-I'm sorry, Kotani! -I'm sorry! Let's go.
-对不起 小谷 -对不起 走
Today's main event is about to start. See you there.
今天重头戏就要开始啦 待会见
Anyway, I'll hire some people to fix what we can fix.
总之我会找人把能修的东西修好
I'll be back as soon as I'm done with my stuff.
等事情处理完 我就会回来啦
You two will be fine until then, right?
在那之前 你们两个没问题吗？
Smile, would you?
笑一个 好吗？
Okay?
好吗？
I'll be back in a sec. Handle things till then.
我马上回来 在那之前就交给你们啦
SUMIDAGAWA HIGH SCHOOL
（隅田川高中）
Excuse me.
不好意思
Want some work?
你们想要打工吗？
-Work? -What kind?
-打工？ -什么样的打工？
Well…
这个…
It's a really fun job. Really fun!
这个工作非常有趣 超好玩
Keep this secret just between us. Don't tell anyone.
要帮我保密哦 别告诉任何人
You'll get the best experience of this festival.
你们会得到这次文化祭最棒的体验
-Experience? -The best experience!
-体验？ -最棒的体验
You can't get this experience anywhere else!
别的地方可没有这种体验哦
Whoa! Thanks man!
谢啦 兄弟
You'll be in it as well.
你待会也要上场哦
What? In the play?
什么？演戏吗？
-Your lines are easy. -No way!
-你的台词很简单 -我不行啦
"There's a fight!" That's all.
你只要说“打架啦”
-I can't! -2 p.m. on the dot. Okay?
-下午2点过来 好吗？
-Later! -Wait! Yoshida!
-待会见 -等等 吉田
-Wait a minute! -Nice timing.
-等一下啦 -你来得正好
-Let's tune up. -Wait!
-我们来排练一下 -等等
-Let's go!
-走呀 -等一下
UNDER CONSTRUCTION
（施工中）
-There. Next! -Next!
-好 下一个 -下一个
Let's get this.
换这个
You guys are on fire! You're hot!
你们真有干劲 火力全开
We won't have this chance later in life.
以后可就没有这种机会啦
I guess you're right.
说得也是
Let's do this!
加油
-Let's do this!
-加油
Okay. The tombstones are ready.
好 墓碑准备好啦
Looks like we'll be ready by lunch.
看来我们在午餐前就能准备好
Someone you know?
是你认识的人吗？
Your stepdad that you talked about?
你之前提到的继父吗？
I happened to be nearby.
我刚好在附近
If you've got time, want to get something to eat?
如果你有空 要不要一起去吃东西？
I didn't have breakfast, so I'm starving.
我没吃早餐 所以很饿
I'm not hungry.
我不饿
Oh, I see.
这样啊
Hello?
喂？
It's nice to hear from you.
很高兴接到你的电话
Yes? Okay.
是 好
What?
什么？
Oh, certainly! I'll be right there. Goodbye.
知道啦 我马上过去 再见
Sorry. I've got to get back to work.
抱歉 我得回去工作啦
Here.
这给你
I didn't know what to get.
我不知道要买什么
-Share this with everyone. -Thank you.
-跟同学一起吃 -谢谢
Okay. Have a good time.
那加油啊
After what you told me,
之前听你说那些事
I thought he'd be a jerk.
我还以为他会是个混蛋
But he's a totally cool dad.
但他看起来是个好爸爸
But why sweet buns?
但为什么是甜馒头？
Those are my favorite sweets.
那是我最喜欢的甜点
He really is a cool dad.
他真的是个好爸爸
I'm hungry.
我饿啦
Why don't we get some lunch? Okay?
我们去吃午餐 好吗？
Okay?
好吗？
Okay.
走吗
TARAKO ONIGIRI
（鳕鱼子饭团）
-Somewhere in town
在镇上的某处
-There is a lonely soul
有个寂寞的灵魂
-On the verge of tears
眼泪汪汪
-Strumming on the guitar
弹着吉他
-Love is lost
爱情已逝
-Searching for something
在寻找着什么
-Wandering around
流连忘返
-We're very much alike
我们很相像
-Come on over here
来这里啊
-The night is long and cold
夜晚漫长又寒冷
-Until morning, let's quietly
就这样静静地待到天亮
-Strum on the guitar…
弹着吉他
Tsukishima, please.
我要去月岛 谢谢
Da…
爸…
Dad!
爸爸
A rice ball!
饭团
Driver, can you stop a second?
司机 麻烦停车
Thank you.
谢谢
Bye.
那我走啦
Go ahead.
开车
I couldn't call him "Dad."
我还是没办法叫他一声“爸爸”
Is that right?
是吗？
I must have a hard heart.
我真无情
No, you don't.
没那回事
You said it yourself.
你自己也说啦
It takes time before realizing something is fun.
要经过一段时间 才会了解其中的快乐
This is the same.
这件事也一样
This kind of thing takes time too.
一样也需要时间
Shuji!
修二
-I'll tell them I'm stepping out. -Okay.
-我跟她们说我出去一下 -好
-Hold on a second.
-等我一下
I'll wait.
我等你
Sorry! I was really busy.
抱歉 我真的很忙
You're late, Shuji!
修二 你迟到啦
You've done a great job!
你们做得很棒啊
But absolutely nobody's coming!
但根本没人来
I guess we got kind of a late start.
我们只是开始得比较慢
Become a closer couple!
你们的感情变得更好啦
Congratulations!
恭喜
Make it couples only!
规定只限情侣参加
We'll get even fewer people!
那就更少人会来啦
If you limit it, then everybody wants it! Even allow boy couples and girl couples!
只要有限制 大家就会想来 两个男生或两个女生都行
Dang!
好耶
Couples only!
情侣限定
A couples-only haunted house!
情侣限定鬼屋
That couple!
那对情侣
Look! A couple!
这里有情侣
Come on, everyone! Couples!
过来 各位 限定情侣进入
Then can I change the ending a little?
那我能改下最后那部分吗？
You bet! Make it even more exciting! I'll be back!
当然 让气氛高潮一点 我马上回来
Couples! Come on couples!
情侣限定 快来呀
Sorry!
抱歉
I was waiting.
我一直在等你
-Let's go. -Okay.
-走呀 -好
Where do you want to go first?
你想先去哪里？
Shuji?
修二？
Stop!
别跑
-I told you not to come! -Shuji? What?
-我叫你不要来 -修二 什么？
Sorry!
抱歉
Wait! Shuji!
等等 修二
You're not supposed to come without a guardian!
没有监护人你不能随便进来
You're here, Shuji.
有你在啊 哥
I told you, I'm busy.
我说过我很忙
There he is! The peasant!
他在那里 农民在那里
-What? -You promised to play a peasant!
-什么？ -你答应过要演农民的
What? I'm a peasant?
什么？我是农民？
One peasant captured!
抓到一位农民啦
-No way! -Get changed or we'll be late!
-我不要 -快换衣服 要来不及啦
Take him away!
把他带走
-Take him away! -You go home now!
-把他带走 -你现在就回家
Go home, you!
马上回家
Step right up for the haunted house!
快来参观鬼屋
There's a long wait,
有很多人在排队哦
so if it's your second time, come back later!
玩过一次的人 晚点再来
Incidentally, I am Dracula!
顺带一提 我是德古拉
We're in the same class. Let us go in.
我们是同班同学 让我们进去啦
Yes.
-是啊
No! Back of the line!
不行 给我到最后面去
Ms. Kuroki is in line with her boyfriend!
黑木老师跟男朋友在排队哦
Go away!
让开啦
Hurry up and kill them!
快点杀了他们
You tramp! Just because I was nice, don't take advantage of me!
你这个坏女人 别因为我是好人 就占我便宜
I'm really sorry.
真的很抱歉
Let's go to the haunted house.
我们去鬼屋
What? You mean our haunted house?
什么？你是说我们班的鬼屋吗？
Yes. I heard the end is really moving.
对啊 听说最后很感人
-It's moving? A haunted house? -So I heard.
-感人？鬼屋？ -别人是这么说的
-Fashion show! You're up next! -Okay.
-时装秀的同学准备上场啦 -好
This way, please.
-这边请
Shuji!
修二
Get good photos!
你要好好拍照哦
I'll hate you forever if they're blurry.
如果照片是模糊的 我会恨你一辈子
Okay. They won't be blurry.
好 不会糊的
Sorry. I'm really sorry.
抱歉 我真的很抱歉
-Sorry. -Shuji! Wait!
-抱歉 -修二
Shuji!
等等 修二
Camera!
相机
Excuse me. I'll take that.
不好意思 我要买那台
Oh, right. I'm a peasant now.
我现在是农民
I'll bring you the money later. I swear I'll bring it!
我晚点再来付钱 我保证一定会来的
Please.
拜托啦
Excuse me!
借过
-Where's 2-B? -That way.
-2年B班在哪里？ -那边
KONNYAKU
（魔芋）
Use these.
用这个
We've got konnyaku!
我们收到了魔芋
When I heard the haunted house got destroyed,
我听说鬼屋被砸毁的时候
I did what little I could and hustled over.
我就慢吞吞地赶来啦
But…
但是
it doesn't look destroyed.
这里看起来没什么问题啊
We've already fixed it.
我们已经修好啦
I see.
这样啊
Guess I'm too late and lost my chance.
看来我来得太慢 错失良机啦
What's this?
这是什么？
You're late because you drew that, aren't you?
你是因为画这个才会慢吞吞的吗？
Stab.
我刺
What? What's that?
什么？那是什么？
You know, that was really nice.
真的很好玩
-That was really moving. -Yes, it really was.
-真令人感动 -对 没错
-What's so moving about a haunted house? -I heard the ending is pretty cool.
-鬼屋有什么好感动的？ -听说最后挺酷的
-Right? -Yes.
-对吗？ -对啊
-Let's go in. -I want to go too!
-我们进去 -我也想去
-I want to go!
-我也想 -我想去看看
If you want to go, then go.
你们想去就去呀
-Yes! Let's go! -Let's go!
-好耶 我们走 -走
-Dang! That's what youth is all about. -I was really moved!
-天啊 原来这就是青春的感觉 -真的很感动
Yes, very moved…
是啊 真感人
Sorry.
抱歉
Quit shouting, you geezer!
吵死啦 臭老头
Listen. Even us geezers want to shout sometimes.
听着 我们这些老头 也会有想大喊的时候
Fuck off, you bald geezer!
滚开 秃老头
My hair's just very short.
我只是头发比较短
Ouch!
好伤人
It's almost time for the ending!
今天的活动
Wait! What about our live show?
等等 那我们的表演？
We ran out of time.
没时间表演啦
-What? All is lost! -Watch out!
-什么？呜呼哀哉 -小心啊
CLOSED
（结束）
We're done, at last.
终于结束啦
Oh, you guys are all done too?
你们这边也结束了吗？
It's all thanks to the guys you hired.
都要多亏你找来这些人
You all have been a big help. Thanks.
你们真的帮了大忙 谢谢
Like you said, it was fun. Right?
你说得对 我们玩得开心 对吗？
I'm really glad we met you guys.
我真的很高兴认识你们
We may never meet again though.
虽然我们可能不会再见面啦
Oh, well.
是啊
Guess we got to go back to our lives again.
看来我们得回到原本的生活
That's a nice camera. Right?
那是一台好相机 对吗？
Take a photo.
-来拍照 -好啊
Okay.
好
Stand up.
站起来
-Crouch lower. -Okay.
-蹲低一点 -好
More.
再低一点
There.
可以啦
Five. Four. Three.
五 四 三…
Let's see it.
来看看呀
You guys!
是你们
It's Catherine!
是凯瑟琳
I see.
我懂啦
This year,
今年
those guys came again.
那些家伙又来啦
Principal Iehara here. I'm coming in.
我是家原校长 我进来啦
You saw them, didn't you?
你们看到他们啦 对吗？
You saw them?
有看到吗？
They were our students 20 years ago.
他们是20年前的学生
Twenty years ago?
20年前？
Their uniforms were brown, right?
他们穿着咖啡色的制服 对吗？
Did they say they were Yamamoto, Komai, and Kaneko?
他们说自己是山本、驹井和金子吗？
Yes, they did.
对 没错
I knew it!
我就知道
When it's festival time…
每当举办文化祭时
Those guys show up every year.
那些家伙每年都会出现
Are they ghosts?
他们是鬼吗？
No. They're alive.
不 他们还活着
They're alive?
他们还活着？
I think Komai is a neurosurgeon at a university hospital.
驹井好像是大学附属医院的 脑神经外科医生
Yes. Yamamoto is a magazine editor at a publishing company.
对 山本是出版社的杂志编辑
But they were all high school students.
但他们都是高中生的样子呀
That's because they're living spirits.
因为他们是生魂
Living spirits?
生魂？
They're way too busy with work, so there's no way they can come.
他们工作很忙 不可能会来的
They must have really loved their high school festival.
他们一定很喜欢高中的文化祭
It is only once in a lifetime
毕竟一生只有一次
when you can be with friends and become engrossed in meaningless fun.
可以跟朋友在一起 沉浸在毫无意义的乐趣中
They can't forget that, so every year,
他们忘不了这种感觉 所以每年…
they come here in just spirit alone.
他们的生魂都会来这里
THIRD YEAR, CLASS A
（3年A班）
Those guys…
这几个家伙
Koji!
浩二
You didn't go home?
你没回家吗？
Come with me!
跟我来
I wanted to see the haunted house!
我想看鬼屋
Then you should have seen it and gone home!
那你看完就应该回家啊
But it was couples only.
但鬼屋限情侣参加
Oh, right.
对哦
Then let's go in.
那我们进去
-Yes! -Okay.
-好 -走呀
You go first, Koji.
浩二 你先走
-What? -Yes. Hurry up.
-什么？ -对 快点
-Oh, man! -Hurry!
-天啊 -快点
Hold on a second.
等一下
You go first.
你先走啦
I think it's looking at us.
它好像在看我们
Okay.
好
Thank goodness.
还好
-Don't push me. -But I'm afraid something's behind me.
-别推我 -但我怕我背后有东西出现
That scared me!
吓我一跳
Splat!
啊！
That's disgusting! Darn you!
真恶心 可恶
Cut that out!
别闹啦
This must be it.
应该是这个
It opened.
打开啦
There's someone!
那里有人
It's just a mirror.
只是一面镜子
Something's written on it.
上面写着东西
"The chances of you meeting the person you are holding hands with now
“你和牵手的人相遇的几率
were far greater than one in a million.
远小于百万分之一
Once you're out in the light, make sure you don't let go of their hand."
走出去后 千万不能放开彼此的手”
Let's go.
走
Yes.
好
Did you have fun?
好玩吗？
Yes. That was fun.
很好玩
Right?
-对吗？ -对啊 设计这个鬼屋的人真是天才
-I'm a genius! -A genius! Yay!
-我们是天才 -天才
-Let's go again! -Genius!
-再玩一次
Hurry! Come on!
快点 走呀
Hurry!
快点
One more time!
再一次
You've got a date with Shuji after this, right?
你等下要跟修二去约会？
-Well, yes. -I'm so envious.
-是啊 -好羡慕哦
I'd like to fall in love too.
我也好想谈恋爱
That was a nice festival.
今年的文化祭真棒
The students only have it three times,
学生最多只能参加三次
but we've done these dozens of times.
但我们已经参加数十次啦
How many times for you?
你参加了几次？
That's my 800th.
今年是第八百次
It's over! It's finally over!
结束啦 终于结束啦
That was one long day.
真是漫长的一天
It was long for me too.
我也觉得很漫长
You see…
你们知道…
For the longest time, I was digging alone,
长久以来 我都是自己在挖洞
like a mole in the dirt.
就像在土里的鼹鼠一样
Then suddenly, two people showed up.
结果突然遇到了两个人
What?
什么？
"Two people"? You mean us two?
“两个人”？你是说我们吗？
Yes.
对
From now on,
从现在开始
I wonder if we'll just happen to meet people again like this.
不知道我会不会又像这样 巧遇其他人？
If we do,
如果会的话
then it's probably all right to be digging in the dirt by myself, right?
那我自己在土里挖个洞应该没关系？
We probably will meet
我们可能会遇到
all kinds of people.
各式各样的人
Then someday
然后总有一天
we'll never meet again.
我们就再也不会见面啦
-Koji. -Yes?
-浩二 -什么？
Don't you be like me.
你可别变成像我这样的人
Like what?
怎样的人？
Well…
就是…
I mean, don't become an adult
不要变成像我这种
who's only good at getting by but can't ever build anything.
只会耍嘴皮子 却什么都不会做的人
I was shocked by it.
我很震惊
When I saw that Nobuta and Akira, who I thought was stupid,
当我看到野猪和我以为是笨蛋的彰
had made something that worked so well,
做出这么成功的东西
I was totally shocked.
我非常震惊
You're a great guy, Shuji.
哥 你是个很棒的人
What?
什么？
You always keep your promises.
你总是说到做到
You can be a little bit of a poser sometimes though.
虽然你有时候有点做作
But I think you're a nice guy.
但我觉得你是个好人
Oh, Dad's home.
爸回来啦
Yes.
是啊
Let's go.
走
Tomorrow, the classroom will be like it was before.
教室明天就会恢复原样了
Nobuta will be bullied again.
野猪一样会被霸凌
Akira will be a nuisance like he always is.
彰仍然会是个讨厌鬼
And I'll be the popular guy.
而我照样会是人气王
Though there's no way that could ever change…
虽然事情不可能有任何改变
I was really insecure.
但我非常没有安全感
I've got nothing…
我什么都没有
so I was incredibly insecure.
所以我非常不安
Whoa! This sight will blow your mind!
这画面太震撼啦
Are you guys dating?
你们在交往吗？
-You should tell Nobuta that you love her. -What?
-你应该跟野猪说你喜欢她 -什么？
Shuji, don't you know?
修二 你不知道吗？
Subtitle translation by: Brian Athey
字幕翻译：张欣怡